Finding Aid for A. Alfred Taubman College of Architecture + Urban Planning Records 1876-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Photographs and Negatives
  - Photographs and Negatives circa 1970-2004, 1987-2004
    - People
      - Visiting Lecturers, Professors, and Scholars
        - Jeff, Gloria February 1997 (Box 78)
        - Lee, Myung Sik February 1997 (Box 78)
        - Lima, Zeuler R.M.A. February 1997 (Box 78)
        - Maruyama, Kinya 1996 (Box 78)
        - Miscellaneous (Amarjit Kalsi; Neal Richman; Jack Travis) 2000 (Box 78)
        - Rahim, Ali February 1997 (Box 78)
        - Rampson-Gage, Wendy February 1997 (Box 78)
        - Vakil, Anna 1990 (Box 78)
    - Projects
      - Faculty and Staff Work
        - North Campus Redux circa 2002 (Box 78)
          (3 CD's; images from Katie Slattery's hard drive; May also included documents relating to other projects)
      - Student Work
        - Alaxander Zopini Studio, Winter 2000 (Box 78)
        - Architectural Renderings: The Acropolis in Athens 1994 (Box 78)
          (work from a course taught by Professor Emeritus Herbert W. Johe)
        - "Architecture of Objects," 1994 (experimental course) (Box 78)
        - "The Briggsville Plan," 1988-1989 (Box 78)
        - CAD Design Studio, Fall 1988 (Box 78)
          (includes images of Kellogg site)
        - Daylight Simulation March 2000 (Box 78)
        - Miscellaneous, no date (Box 78)
        - Models and Drawings (Box 79)
          - Fall 1993, 2 folders (Box 79)
          - 1996-1997 (Box 79)
          - 1998 (Box 79)
        - Penland circa 1995 (building project in North Carolina) (Box 79)
        - Prague -- Jason Young, no date (Box 79)
        - Prague Map -- Chris Knapp 1996-1997 (Box 79)
        - Shape of Flow -- Han Suh November 1996 (Box 79)
        - Sherando Lake Forest Camp circa 1994 (Box 79)
        - "Silva Studies," Fall 1996 (Box 79)
        - "Stair Study," Winter 1996 (projects from Arch. 322) (Box 79)
        - Urban and Regional Planning (URP) Student Projects circa 1999 (Box 79)
          (includes Expanded Horizons in Chicago, and Norris House)
    - Publications
      - Portico
        - Fall 1988 (Box 79)
        - Fall 1990 (Box 79)
        - Summer 1991 (Box 79)
        - Spring 1992 (Box 79)
        - Summer 1992 (Box 79)
        - Fall 1992 (Box 79)
        - Spring/Summer 1993 (Box 79)
        - 1997 (vol. 3) (Box 79)
        - 1999 (vol. 2) (Box 79)
        - 2000 (vol. 2) (Box 79)
        - 2001 (vol. 2) (Box 79)
        - 2002 (vol. 3) (Box 79)
      - Miscellaneous
        - Dimensions
          - 1988 (Box 79)
          - 1994 (Box 79)
        - Bulletin 1996-1997 (Box 79)
        - Masters of Urban Design (M.U.D.) program brochure 1999-2000 (Box 79)
- Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning Website
  The Taubman College Archived Website series documents the academic programs, accomplishments, resources, events, and people at the Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning. Content includes important news and announcements, publications (such as newsletters and course catalogs), and information about admissions, curriculum, degree requirements, faculty, and the overall mission of the College. The website series is arranged chronologically, with captures from 2002 and 2003 stored on CD. Starting in 2010, this archived website will be captured on a regular, ongoing basis as part of the University of Michigan Web Archives, hosted at http://webarchives.cdlib.org/a/universityofmichigan/.
  - Website capture May 15, 2002, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 2)
  - Website capture May 22, 2003, 1 optical disks CDs (Box 2)
  - Archived Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning home page 2010-[ongoing]
  - Archived websites related to the Taubman College of Architecture and Urban Planning 2010-[ongoing]
- Art and Architecture Building Renovations 1996-1998
  The Art and Architecture Building Renovations series, 1996-1998 (0.5 linear feet) includes files documenting the beginning of a project to expand and modify the Art and Architecture Building. Enrique Norton and his firm TEN Arquitectos submitted several reports and proposals on the desired renovation. The project was halted due to prohibitive costs. This series includes the reports generated by the TEN Arquitectos, along with reports, correspondence, and other documentation from staff within the College. The proposals submitted by the TEN Arquitectos were included in the 1996-2000 accession as a part of the ARCHITECTURAL DRAWINGS series.
  - General 1996-1998 (Box 66)
  - Computing Service Status 1996 (Box 66)
  - Cost Estimates 1997 (Box 66)
  - Gross Space Allocations 1996-1997 (Box 66)
  - Program for Regeneration 1997 (Box 66)
  - TEN Arquitectos Reports 1997
    - Architectural Analysis and Program (Box 66)
    - Design Concepts (Box 66)
    - Program Study (Box 66)
    - Program for Regeneration -- Annex I (Box 66)
    - Program for Regeneration -- Annex II (Box 66)
    - Project Proposal (Box 66)
- Department of Urban Planning 1967-1988
  The Department of Urban Planning series, 1967-1988 (2.5 linear feet) documents the founding and development of the department in the mid-sixties. A program in urban planning existed within the college since 1946, but growing interest in planning led to the establishment of the Department of Urban Planning in 1968. The series is split into two sub-series: General Files and Course Files. The General Files, 1967-1988 include materials on programs within the department, department correspondence and reports, and student statistics. Also included are Urban Planning Program Council meeting minutes from August 29, 1968 to December 17, 1983. Researchers should note that the Urban Planning Program Council Meeting Minutes were called Urban Planning Faculty Meeting Minutes until September 3, 1976. The Course Files, 1967-1986 contain information on the various courses offered through the Department of Urban Planning. The files include proposals for new courses, course syllabi, and course materials. The date range indicated for the Course Files sub-series is inclusive, but not all dates are represented in the individual files.
  - General Files
    - Admissions and Enrollment Reports 1969-1982 (Box 55)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2057 ]
    - American Society of Planning Officials (ASPO) Survey Information 1968-1978 (scattered) (Box 66)
    - Application for Re-Recognition of Master of Urban Planning Degree November 1982 (Box 66)
    - Association of Collegiate Schools of Planning (ACSP) Guide Updates 1976-1978 (Box 66)
    - Chairmanship Report 1979, 1982 (Box 66)
    - Concentration Materials 1977-1982 (Box 66)
    - Core Content of Urban, Technological, and Environmental Planning (UTEP) 1985-1986 (Box 66)
    - Curriculum 1967-1980 (scattered), 2 folders (Box 66)
    - Degree Program Posters, no date (Box 66)
    - External Graduate Program 1976-1977 (Box 66)
    - Formation of Department of Planning 1958-1968 (Box 66)
    - Memos to Dean Robert C. Metcalf 1975-1979 (Box 66)
    - Memos to Faculty 1977-1983 (Box 66)
    - Memos to Urban Planning Program Council 1975-1979 (Box 66)
    - Minority Affairs 1977-1981 (Box 66)
    - Minority Education 1968-1972 (Box 55)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2047 ]
    - Other Planning Programs at the University of Michigan 1966-1971 (Box 66)
    - Ph.D. Program in Urban and Regional Planning -- Program Description September 1977 (Box 67)
    - Planning and Policy Coordinating Council 1981-1982 (Box 67)
    - Planning and Policy Studies Brochure 1982, 2 folders (Box 67)
    - Rackham Block Grants 1969-1981 (Box 67)
    - Rackham Correspondence 1975-1982 (Box 67)
      (includes a report from the Rackham Review Committee)
    - Rackham: Criteria for Evaluation of Masters Degrees 1970-1972 (Box 67)
    - Recruitment and Admissions Policies 1977-1981 (Box 67)
    - Review of the Program Master's in Urban Planning, Summer 1979 (Box 67)
    - Rules -- Urban Planning Program 1976-1977 (Box 67)
    - Status and Quality Reports 1982-1983, 1988 (Box 67)
    - Student Caucus 1970-1979 (scattered) (Box 67)
    - Student -- Faculty Curriculum Committee 1970-1973 (Box 67)
    - Student Lists 1976-1980 (Box 67)
    - Student Statistics 1969-1985 (Box 55)
      [SR RESTRICTED until July 1 2060 ]
    - Surveys -- Urban Planning Graduates 1980-1982 (Box 67)
    - Teaching Assistantships: Criteria and Information 1969-1982 (scattered) (Box 67)
    - Tenure Review Materials 1974-1976 (Box 67)
    - Undergraduate Program 1977-1979 (Box 67)
    - Urban Planning: General 1978, 1983-1989 (Box 67)
    - Urban Planning Program Council Meeting Agendas (Faculty Meeting Agendas) August 29, 1968-October 14, 1980 (Box 67)
    - Urban Planning Program Council Meeting Minutes (Faculty Meeting Minutes)
      - August 29, 1968-May 24, 1973 (Box 67)
      - August 31, 1973-May 29, 1975 (Box 67)
      - August 29, 1975-October 14, 1980 (Box 67)
      - August 15, 1980-December 17, 1983 (Box 67)
  - Course Files 1967-1986
    - U.P. 263, Energy and Environment (Box 67)
    - U.P. 423, Introduction to Urban Planning (Box 67)
    - U.P. 424, Urban Planning Workshop (Box 67)
    - U.P. 425, Evolution of the Urban Environment (Box 67)
    - U.P. 426, Urban Transportation (Box 67)
    - U.P. 432, World Food Systems (Box 67)
    - U.P. 500 and 600, Planning Theory I and II (Box 67)
    - U.P. 503, Environmental Analysis for Planners/Analytics I: An Introduction to Analytical Methods for Planners (Box 67)
    - U.P. 504, Problem Solving for Planners (Box 67)
    - U.P. 505, Urban Planning Analysis I/Planning Communications (Box 68)
    - U.P. 506, Urban Planning Analysis II (Box 68)
    - U.P. 509, Statistical Analysis in Architecture, Planning, and Engineering (Box 68)
    - U.P. 512/Arch. 512, Urban Design (Box 68)
    - C.P. 513/U.P. 513, Planning Administration/Legal Aspects of the Planning Process (Box 68)
    - U.P. 519, Principles of Urban Design (Box 68)
    - U.P. 520, History of Urban Development (Box 68)
    - U.P. 522, Introduction to Physical Planning (Box 68)
    - U.P. 524, Physical Planning Workshop (Box 68)
    - U.P. 526/Arch. 526, Building and Planning Economics (Box 68)
    - U.P. 537, Introduction to Housing Systems (Box 68)
    - U.P. 538, National Housing Policy (a.k.a. Housing and Public Policy) (Box 68)
    - U.P. 540, Introduction to Planning Theory/Professional Planning Roles, Styles, and Theories (Box 68)
    - U.P. 543, History of Urban Form (Box 68)
    - U.P. 555, Social Aspects of Urban Planning/Public Works Planning (Box 68)
    - U.P. 570, Urban Transportation (Box 68)
    - U.P. 571, Urban Transportation Systems Planning (Box 68)
    - U.P. 573, Urban and Regional Theory I (Box 68)
    - U.P. 574, Decentralism (Box 68)
    - U.P. 575, The Emerging City/Region (Box 68)
    - U.P. 602, Video Simulation Methods (Box 68)
    - U.P. 605, Urban Planning Analysis II (Box 68)
    - U.P. 610, Capital Program Budgeting/Urban Finance and Budgeting Systems (Box 68)
    - U.P. 611, Strategies for Economic Development and Business Incentives (Box 68)
    - U.P. 612, Urban Planning Analysis I (Box 68)
    - U.P. 613, Urban Planning Analysis II (Box 68)
    - U.P. 614, Contemporary Legal Developments (Box 68)
    - U.P. 620, History of Urban Development (Box 68)
    - U.P. 622/C.P. 622, Planning Studio II: Comprehensive Plan Preparation/Physical Aspects of Urban Planning (Box 68)
    - U.P. 624, Advance Physical Planning Workshop (Box 68)
    - U.P. 625, Problems in Planning Theory (Box 68)
    - U.P. 630, Urban Planning Studio (Box 68)
    - U.P. 631, Urban Planning Studio (Box 68)
    - U.P. 633, Coastal Zone Planning and Design (Box 68)
    - U.P. 634, Comprehensive Plan Preparation I (Box 68)
    - U.P. 635, Comprehensive Plan Preparation II (Box 68)
    - U.P. 640, Strategic Decision Making in Planning (Box 68)
    - U.P. 655, Social Aspects of Urban Planning/Neighborhood Planning Workshop (Box 68)
    - U.P. 656 (formerly C.P. 623), Housing Problems Seminar (Box 68)
    - U.P. 658, Urban and Regional Planning in Developing Countries (Box 68)
    - U.P. 663, Theory and Practice of Gaming/Simulation (Box 68)
    - U.P. 665 and U.P. 750, Behavior and the Urban Environment (Box 68)
    - U.P. 671, Research Seminar in Transportation (Box 68)
    - U.P. 673, Historic Preservation and Urban Conservation (Box 68)
    - U.P. 674, Design of Alternative Communication (Box 68)
    - U.P. 675, Urban and Regional Theory II (Urban Policy Analysis) (Box 68)
    - U.P. 680, Urban Issues Seminar (Box 68)
    - U.P. 709 (655), Social Policy and Urban Planning (Box 68)
    - U.P. 712 (624), Physical Planning Workshop (Box 68)
    - U.P. 713, Planning and Programming for Metropolitan Areas (Box 68)
    - U.P. 714 (630), The Design of Urban Environments I (Box 68)
    - U.P. 719 (see U.P. 731), Problems in Urban Development (Box 68)
    - U.P. 722, Comprehensive Plan Preparation (Box 68)
    - U.P. 723, Regional Planning Seminar (Box 68)
    - U.P. 724, The Design of Urban Environments II (Box 68)
    - U.P. 726, Introduction to Physical Design/Basic Graphics (Box 68)
    - U.P. 731 (old 719), Conflict and Consensus in Urban Problems (Box 68)
    - U.P. 734, The Design of Urban Environments III (Box 68)
    - U.P. 736 and U.P. 737 (new 682 and 683), Directed Study (Box 68)
- Audio-Visual Material
  The Audio-Visual Material series (1 linear foot) includes audio tapes, video tapes, DVD's, and a film reel. Of particular interest in this series is a DVD celebrating TCAUP's centennial in 2006, three video tapes containing the three parts of the 2004 "Michigan Debates on Urbanism," and a video focusing on Albert Kahn called "Architects We Knew." There is also a lecture on audio tape delivered by Peter Eisenman in 1991, and a video of a lecture on the North Campus Redux effort delivered by Doug Kelbaugh.
  - Audio Tapes
    - Architecture and Urban Planning (UM): Reinventing Practice March 16, 1996, 4 tapes (Box 80)
    - Peter Eisenman Lecture November 22, 1991 (Box 80)
  - DVDs
    - "The Greater Good: 100 Years of Architecture and Planning at Michigan" (DVD use copy) 2006 (Box 80)
    - Stamps Auditorium Dedication and Announcement of the WorkPlay Competition Winners March 27, 2008 (Box 80)
  - Motion Picture
    - "Exxon," Architecture and Planning Research Laboratory (APRL) (numbered SPN16677) undated (Box 80)
  - Video Tapes
    - Architects We Knew 2004 (G. Hildebrand on Albert Kahn; introduction by Douglas Kelbaugh) (Box 80)
    - Commencement May 4, 1996 (Box 80)
    - "The Greater Good: 100 Years of Architecture and Planning at Michigan," 2006, DV-CAM master (Box 80)
    - Michigan Debates on Urbanism
      - Part I: Everyday Urbanism January 30, 2004 (Box 80)
      - Part II: New Urbanism March 31, 2004 (Box 80)
      - Part III: Post Urbanism April 20, 2004 (Box 80)
    - North Campus Redux -- UM Lecture by Douglas Kelbaugh October 7, 2002 (Box 80)
    - Sprawling of America (Douglas Kelbaugh and Chris Cook) June 3, 2001 (Box 80)
      (Spotlight on the News, WXYZ-TV Channel 7)
- Articles, Reports and Speeches 1998-2008
  The Articles, Reports, and Speeches series, 1998-2008 (0.5 linear feet) includes various speeches and published materials written by Douglas S. Kelbaugh during his tenure as dean. Kelbaugh's writings were organized into categories including: articles written for the College publication "Portico," other published essays and articles, book chapters and introductions, commencement addresses, reports to the faculty, conference remarks and lecture introductions, and miscellaneous writings. Within each category the materials are organized chronologically.
  - Douglas S. Kelbaugh
    - 1998-2008
      - Portico (Box 62)
      - Published Essays and Articles (Box 62)
      - Book Chapters and Book Introductions (Box 62)
      - Commencement Addresses (Box 62)
      - Reports to the Faculty (Box 62)
      - Conference Remarks and Lecture Introductions (Box 62)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 62)
- Artifacts
  The Artifacts series consists of two banners from the TCAUP Centennial Celebration held in 2006. The banners were hung from lamp posts lining the campus streets. The banners are oversized and are stored separately from the other series in this addition.
  - TCAUP Centennial Celebration Banners 2006 (Box 80)
    (2 oversize banners; stored in separate location)
- E-Mail Correspondence
  The E-mail Correspondence series (1.8 GB; 22,438 files) contains messages from Dean Kelbaugh's sent-mail directory dating from November 18, 2003 to August 2, 2008. The messages were originally arranged in reverse chronological order, and this order was maintained upon transfer to the Bentley. Correspondence in the series includes discussion on North Campus planning issues, the addition to the Art and Architecture building, development of the design charrette program, planning for the establishment of a Detroit Center, and Ann Arbor city planning developments such as Lowertown. There are also a number of messages regarding faculty recruitment and retention. During processing of the series no messages were deleted or weeded, therefore several instances of routine correspondence are also included. The series is an excellent example of the discourse maintained by Kelbaugh with colleagues in the architecture and urban planning field, as well as his attentive communication with administrators, faculty, and staff at the University of Michigan. Given the sensitive nature of some of this material, access is restricted in accordance with University policies. Each message is a separate file.
  - Douglas Kelbaugh, (sent mail) November 18, 2003-August 2, 2008, 22438 digital files 1.8 GB
Related Material
The Bentley Library holds the papers for a number of former deans and faculty members including Wells I. Bennett, Gunnar Birkerts, Leonard K. Eaton, C. Theodore Larson, Emil Lorch, Reginald L. Malcolmson, William Muschenheim, Walter Sanders, Harlow Olin Whittemore, and Philip Newell Youtz. Also related to the record group is a collection of student papers, 1924-1980, primarily prepared for classes in architectural history. Papers include historical description and appended visual material. The library also holds two linear feet of records generated by the Alpha Rho Chi fraternity, 1909-1986.